Hello English learners, welcome back to EnglishPod.
My name is Marco.
And I'm Erica.
Today, we're bringing you an upper intermediate lesson and something that we all do.
Right, talking to ourselves.
Talking to ourselves, right?
Yeah.
I think everyone does it.
You think to yourself or you talk to yourself.
Yeah.
And we're going to be doing that today, but we're going to be looking at some specific vocabulary.
Erica, why don't you tell us about that?
Well, unfortunately, we're going to be following a guy as he's in a really embarrassing situation and we're going to hear him call himself some bad names in his mind.
So he's a little bit nervous and he thinks he is not very smart, right?
That's right.
Okay, so before we start with this dialogue, there are a couple of words that we should look at in vocabulary preview.
Vocabulary preview.
All right, we're going to hear both of these words in the dialogue.
And the first one is famished.
Famished.
Okay, so famished is an adjective.
That's right, meaning very, very, very hungry.
Very, very hungry.
Okay, so just very hungry, very easy.
Yes.
Famished.
Now, what about our next one?
Sexist.
Another adjective to describe a person, right?
Right.
Or a thing, I guess.
Like, yeah, an idea.
Okay, so a sexist person would be?
Somebody who judges people by their sex.
Okay.
So like all women are stupid, for example.
Which is not true, of course.
No, of course not.
Right?
So sexist works both ways.
Yes.
A woman can be sexist, a man could be sexist.
Exactly.
Meaning the women thinks all men are stupid.
Which is also not true.
Yes.
Let's just be clear about that.
All right.
So now that we've taken a look at these two phrases, let's start with our dialogue and we'll be back to talk about all the great words.
Miss, your salad.
Mmm.
Looks good.
I'm positively famished.
And for you, sir.
Thank you.
Enjoy.
I can't believe she's on a date with me.
I'm so lucky.
I must be the luckiest guy in the world.
I want to scream at the top of my lungs.
I'm the luckiest dude in the world.
Oh, shut up.
Don't be such a dumbass.
She's so hot.
Wait, I can't say that.
That's sexist.
She's so hot.
She's making me sexist.
Oh my God.
I'm such a tool.
Okay, get it together.
She's eating salad.
Oh, right, I have a salad. Oh, crap!
Which fork do I use?
Damn it!
She's going to think I'm a moron.
What the hell are all these forks for?
Which one did she use?
Okay, chill, be cool, be cool. Just take a fork. Eat your salad. Um... Mm? Sorry, you were saying?
You're eating my salad.
Oh, yes, it's delicious.
Okay, embarrassing first date, huh?
Yeah, I mean I really do feel sorry for this guy.
Well, it happens to us.
Sometimes we are in the company of a very beautiful girl and we just get really nervous.
Alright, well, you know, psychologists call this negative self-talk.
Really?
Yeah, this sort of calling yourself names and talking negatively about yourself.
But actually you can use some of this language to talk negatively about others.
Yeah.
So why don't we look now at this language in Language Takeaway.
Language Takeaway.
So on Language Takeaway today we have five words.
Let's start with our first one.
Dumbass.
Okay, now this isn't a very polite word I would say.
Definitely not polite.
Okay, but what is a dumbass?
Well, it's obviously a dumb, stupid idiot.
Okay, so it's a person that is not very intelligent.
And our next word is also quite similar.
Moron.
A moron.
If a person is a dumbass or a person is a moron, what's the difference?
Well, basically a moron is someone who is not smart, who is very unintelligent.
Okay.
So they don't know what one plus one is.
All right.
But a dumbass is a person who does stupid things.
Okay.
So maybe a dumbass like you're planning a bank robbery and the dumbass forgets to bring the gun.
That is a dumbass.
All right.
So maybe moron is a little bit less offensive and it's actually you'll find it in the dictionary, right?
Yeah.
Whereas a dumbass I don't think you'll find it.
Yeah, it's slang.
It's slang.
Exactly.
Now what about this next?
It's also a negative name you can call people.
A tool.
Tool.
This is very strange because I don't know how a tool can be something negative towards a person.
Yeah.
But it actually means the opposite, right?
If a person is called a tool, it means they are useless, right?
Yeah.
So if you ever call the tool, they're saying that you're useless.
Exactly.
You're good for nothing.
All right.
Well, these are three interesting words.
So why don't we hear some examples of each of these words in use?
Example one.
I hate Tom.
He's such a dumbass.
Last week he borrowed my mobile phone and dropped it in the pool.
Example two.
I don't like Kevin very much.
He can be a real moron at times.
Example three.
It was looking for a joke, but he didn't even have a resume prepared.
He's such a tool.
Okay, so great examples and here at EnglishPod, we're bringing you real street talk.
Exactly.
Language as it is spoken by today's youth.
Okay.
Now let's take a look at our last two words.
All right.
Well, these phrases you can use when you're trying to calm yourself down and make yourself relax a little bit, right?
Right.
Let's take a look at the next one.
Chill.
Okay.
So again, relax.
Calm down.
Relax.
Chill.
Yes.
And then you also need to be cool.
Be cool.
Now if you can tell the pattern is related to temperature, right?
Chill is cold.
Cool is similar to cold.
So again, that's what it means to relax.
To calm down your emotions.
Make your emotions not so hot.
Exactly.
All right.
So chill.
Be cool.
Exactly.
And you use them together like that, don't you?
Yeah.
Now chill also has another way of using it, right?
Exactly.
I'm chilling with my friends.
Yeah.
We're chilling here in the EnglishPod studio.
Which means we're just relaxing.
We are just having fun.
Not doing anything, right?
Exactly.
But you can't say chilling.
You have to drop the G. Yeah.
You have to drop.
Right.
You can't say I'm chilling.
You have to say I'm chilling.
I'm chilling.
Okay.
So that's all for language takeaway.
But now let's take a look at some of the really useful phrases that we saw in this dialogue in Fluency Builder.
Okay.
So this guy is so happy he's on this date that he wants to scream at the top of his lungs.
Scream at the top of my lungs.
So basically he just wants to scream.
To shout really loudly.
Really loudly.
Yeah.
He's so excited, right?
Exactly.
Okay.
So for example, sometimes you're at a concert, right?
Yep.
And you need to talk to your friend and you're screaming at the top of your lungs because the other person can't hear you.
Exactly.
So you're lost in the woods and you need to scream at the top of your lungs so that someone will hear you and find you.
All right.
Very good.
Okay.
So scream at the top of my lungs.
Our next phrase.
Get it together.
So if I tell you, Erica, you need to get it together.
Basically you're telling me to calm down, relax.
So pull your emotions together, get your ideas straight.
Right.
So it kind of gives you this idea that you got to pull, like you said, pull your emotions together in a little box and tie them up.
All right.
So get it together.
Yep.
So Marco, when would you use this phrase, get it together?
I guess when somebody is either very emotional, maybe crying or very nervous, you tell the person, oh, get it together, relax.
Or when somebody maybe is not doing something good in their life, like making bad decisions or not being responsible, you tell that person, you need to get it together.
Exactly.
Right.
I couldn't have said it better myself.
Okay.
So now why don't we move on to our next phrase?
And this is really, really high frequency.
I think you would hear it all the time.
All right.
So what the hell?
What the hell?
So why would you say what the hell?
Well, obviously you're asking a question, right?
Because you got your W, you got your what.
But when you say the hell, you're putting emphasis on the what.
So you're asking a really strong question.
Right.
It's not polite.
Yeah.
Okay.
So if I say what the hell is going on?
What's happening?
Really, really what's happening?
Right?
Yeah.
So, and we can change it a little bit.
We can replace the what with another WH like why, how, where, where or when.
Yeah.
Okay.
So why don't we hear some examples of how this expression is used using different WH words?
Example one, where the hell are you?
I've been waiting for hours.
Example two, how the hell did you do that?
That was amazing.
Example three, when the hell are you going to find a job?
I'm tired of paying for everything.
Example four, who the hell are you?
I don't know you.
All right.
Now our final word, also a little bit strong, but pretty high frequency.
Oh yeah.
Very high frequency.
Oh crap.
So it's a little bit strong, but less strong than maybe saying a really bad word.
Right?
Yes.
But it's definitely saying like you made a mistake.
Right?
Yeah.
It's like a really strong, oh no.
Oh no.
Exactly.
A really strong, oh no.
Yeah.
But I guess not many people say, oh no.
Oh no.
I just lost $10 million.
Exactly.
Right?
You would not say that.
Yeah.
So it's a very strong, oh no, but it's not as strong as it could be.
There are other words out there that are stronger, but we are not going to go into them here.
But maybe you guys know, so let us know.
Yes.
We can definitely keep an eye out on the comment section.
But don't write the words in the comment section.
Okay.
So we saw some really great phrases, some really great words, a lot of informal language, but it's very high frequency and you'll use that with your friends or you'll see it in movies, TV shows.
Yeah.
Really common in movies and TV shows.
Exactly.
So let's listen to this dialogue one more time and then we'll come back and talk a little bit more.
Miss, your salad.
Hmm.
Looks good.
I'm positively famished.
And for you, sir.
Thank you.
Enjoy.
I can't believe she's on a date with me.
I'm so lucky.
I must be the luckiest guy in the world.
I want to scream at the top of my lungs, 'I'm the luckiest dude in the world!'
Oh, shut up!
Don't be such a dumbass.
She's so hot!
Wait, I can't say that.
That's sexist.
She's so hot. She's making me sexist.
Oh my god!
I'm such a tool!
Okay, get it together.
She's eating salad. Oh right.
I have a salad.
Oh crap, which fork do I use?
Damn it! She's gonna think I'm a moron.
What the hell are all these forks for?
Which one did she use?
Okay, chill.
Be cool.
Just take a fork.
Eat your salad.
Um...
Mm?
Oh, sorry.
What were you saying?
You're eating my salad.
Oh, yes.
It's delicious.
So these slang words, they're actually very common, right?
Yeah, I think like you said, it's not likely that you'll find them in a dictionary.
Of course. And you can find them in movies, or sometimes when you're having a conversation, a very informal conversation with a native speaker, these words will slip out and these slang terms will come up.
Exactly. And you know what?
There's a great resource out there for wonderful English slang terms, called UrbanDictionary.com.
Exactly. If you ever see a word that maybe you can't find in the conventional dictionary, you're probably gonna find it there.
Yeah, we'll put a link up to it on the site.
Alright. So also, if you have any questions or comments, be sure to come to our website, EnglishPod.com.
Marco and I are there to answer all your questions, and we also got lots of resources, like links to Urban Dictionary.
Right. And also, if you have any questions on any other slang terms that you may have heard, or how to use them, be sure to post it on the comment section.
Well guys, thanks for listening to this lesson, and until next time, goodbye!